[Waco] Branch Davidians: Amo Paul Roden papers, Inclusive: 1946-2008, 2017, undated, Bulk: 1993-2003
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
[Waco] Branch Davidians: Amo Paul Roden papers
Inclusive: 1946-2008, 2017, undated, Bulk: 1993-2003
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3312
Roden, Amo Paul Bishop
2 boxes.
The [Waco] Branch Davidians: Amo Paul Roden papers contain books, sermons, and printed materials collected by influential Branch Davidian Amo Paul Bishop Roden. Particular emphasis is placed on explaining the Davidians’ and Branch Davidians' theology and Roden’s personal investigation of the Waco Siege of 1993.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Excellent.
Biography/Profile
The religious sects known as the Davidians and Branch Davidians were the products of a reform movement within the Seventh-Day Adventist Church. Problems began when a group of Adventists, led by Bulgarian immigrant Victor Houteff, began to challenge the traditional hierarchy of the denomination. Houteff claimed to have received personal revelations from God and published his controversial views in a book entitled The Shepherd’s Rod (1932). Houteff and his followers, the Davidians, believed that the spiritual gift of prophecy was necessary for effective leadership so that King David’s earthly kingdom could be re-established on earth prior to the second coming of Jesus Christ. After the leaders of the Seventh-Day Adventist Church excommunicated his sect, Houteff moved to Waco, Texas, and continued to preach until his death in 1955.
Following Houteff’s death and subsequent divisions among the Davidians, Benjamin Roden and his wife Lois rose to power over a new sect called the Branch Davidians. This couple led the Branch Davidians well into the 1980s. Some of their work including sermons, pamphlets, and personal correspondence are found in the Mark Swett Collection.
The 1980s brought about division within the Branch Davidian sect. A newcomer named Vernon Howell had joined the Branch in 1981. Three years later, a schism occurred within the Branch Davidians, with Howell leading his own group of followers to a new site in Palestine, Texas. Through a series of confrontations between Howell and George Roden, the son of Ben and Lois Roden, control of the Branch Davidians’ headquarters in Waco passed to Howell who legally changed his name to David Koresh in 1990. Rumors concerning polygamy, abuse, and arms dealing within the Branch Davidian group aroused the suspicions of the federal government. Thus, federal agencies such as the Federal Bureau of Investigation and the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives began to monitor the group.
In response to a stockpiling of illegal weapons, the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives secured a search warrant for the investigation of the Branch Davidians’ compound near Waco, Texas. From 1993 February 28th until April 19th, Branch Davidians under the leadership of David Koresh resisted federal agents’ attempts to storm their Mount Carmel Center. The fifty-day siege ended when the compound erupted in flames, killing David Koresh and most of his followers.
Branch Davidian Amo Paul Bishop married George Roden in 1987 October. A month later, the infamous shootout between George Roden and Vernon Howell over leadership of the sect resulted in the expulsion of the Rodens from the Mount Carmel property. After her husband was convicted of murder in 1989 and sent to a mental institution, Amo divorced George but used her marriage in an effort to claim the mantle of spiritual leadership within the Davidian sect following the death of David Koresh. She moved into the rubble of Mount Carmel months after the siege took place and began collecting materials to defend the Davidians’ theology and explain their point of view concerning the events of 1993. Many of these writings were donated to The Texas Collection. For autobiographical material concerning her life as a Branch Davidian, see Roden’s work entitled The Second Standoff.
Scope and Content
The [Waco] Branch Davidians: Amo Paul Roden papers contain sermons, essays, books, and printed materials that examine the Davidians' and Branch Davidians’ theology. Many of the writings were composed by Roden herself after the Siege of 1993. The collection also contains material from Davidian founder Victor Houteff and Branch Davidian leader David Koresh. Much of these materials are sympathetic towards the Branch Davidians.
Arrangement
The [Waco] Branch Davidians: Amo Paul Roden papers are arranged into 1 series: I. Literary Productions.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3312. Acquired 1998-12-15
Related Resources
Items in related collections
[Waco] Branch Davidians: Robert F. Darden III collection, Inclusive: 1932-1993, undated, Bulk:1985-1993, undated
[Waco] Branch Davidians: Kenneth G.C. Newport
[Waco] Branch Davidians: Joe Robert collection, Inclusive: 1932-1997, undated, Bulk: 1979-1995
[Waco] Branch Davidians: Kenneth G.C. Newport
[Waco] Branch Davidians: William Smith collection, Inclusive: 1984-1998, undated, Bulk: 1993-1995
[Waco] Branch Davidians: Kirk D. Lyons collection, Inclusive: 1979-1998, undated, Bulk: 1993-1995
[Waco] Branch Davidians: Mount Carmel Seventh Day Adventist collection, Inclusive: 1938-1998, undated, Bulk: 1959-1961; 1996-1997
[Waco] Branch Davidians: "The Facts About Mt. Carmel" Exhibit collection, Inclusive: 1961-2004, undated, Bulk: 1993-1994
[Waco] Branch Davidians: Ron Armstrong collection, Inclusive: 1931-1960, undated, Bulk: 1931-1933
Related references
Kerstetter, Todd. “That’s Just the American Way: The Branch Davidian Tragedy and Western Religious History.” Western Historical Quarterly vol. 35, no. 4 (2004 Winter): 453-471.
Lawson, Ronald. “Seventh-Day Adventist Responses to Branch Davidian Notoriety: Patterns of Diversity within a Sect Reducing Tension with Society.” Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion vol. 34, no. 3 (1995 September): 323-341.
Local Man Offers Insight into Waco.” Religion News Report vol. 4, no. 223 (2000 July 4).
Roden, Amo Paul Bishop. “About Amo." Accessed 2011 September 7.
Rosenfeld Jean E., Mary Z. Stange, and Ivan Strenski. “Understanding Waco.” Journal of the American Academy of Religion vol. 62, no. 3 (1994 Autumn): 919-946.
Wright, Stuart A. “A Decade after Waco: Reassessing Crisis Negotiations at Mount Carmel in Light of New Government Disclosures.” Nova Religio vol. 7, no. 2 (2003 November): 101-110.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Koresh, David, 1959-1993.
Subjects (Organizations)
Branch Davidians.
Subjects
Mount Carmel Center, Waco, Tex.; Seventh Day Adventists -- History.; Waco Branch Davidian Disaster, Tex., 1993.
Genres
Essays.; Manuscripts.; Programs.; Sermons.
- Literary Productions, 1946-2008, 2017, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Excellent.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains books, sermons and printed materials collected by Amo Paul Bishop Roden. Particular emphasis is placed on the Davidians' and Branch Davidians' theology.
  - Book: Arrive Alive in the Kingdom of God: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Book: Babylon is Fallen: The Legacy of David Koresh: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Book: Christ and the Mosaic Law: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Book: Christ’s Kingdom: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Book: Cracking the Coverup: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Book: George and David: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Book: Joshua’s Crowns: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Book: Let My People Go: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Book: Miracles, Mysteries, and Messiahs: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Book: Opening the Second Seal, The Call from Babylon: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Book: Scrapbook of a Protest: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Book: Seven American Angels: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Book: Seven Scriptures, The Rapture, The Ensign, Etc.: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Book: The Politics of Murder: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Book: The Second Standoff: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Book: The Seven Seals: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Book: The Seven Spirits of God our Harvest Angels: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Book: The Unseen Christ: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Amo Roden's Extreme Healing Cookbook, 2017 March 28 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Manuscript: The Decoded Message of the Seven Seals of the Book of Revelation: David Koresh, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Sermons: Victor Houteff, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Essays: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, 1981- June 2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Essays: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, September 2004- June 2008 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Essays: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, July 2008, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Essays: Amo Paul Bishop Roden, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mount Carmel Center: Essay: "Clinton's Coverup", 1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Mount Carmel Center: Essay: "Cracking the Coverup", undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Mount Carmel Center: Essay: "Crime and Coverup", 1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Mount Carmel Center: Essay: "Mount Carmel Answers", 1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mount Carmel Center: Essay: "Pave it or Save it", undataed (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Mount Carmel Center: Programs, 1998, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Mount Carmel Center: Printed Materials: Welcome Center, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)